Inventory of the Harry E. Krauss III Anglican Collection 1765-1935
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Harry E. Krauss III Anglican Collection, 1765-1935.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 91 K86
33 items.
Letters from the archbishops of Canterbury and York, Anglican and Episcopal bishops and British prime minister, William Ewarts Gladstone chiefly concerning church business.
Gladstone, W. E. (William Ewart), 1809-1898,; Ingram, A. F. Winningham,; Moore, Richard Channing,; Tait, Archibald Campbell,; Canterbury, Charles Manners-Sutton, Viscount, 1780-1845.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Acc. No. 1990-34; Gift: 9 items, 07/24/1990. Acc. No. 1991-30; Gift: 24 items, 05/08/1991.
Scope and Content Information
Letters from the archbishops of Canterbury and York, Anglican and Episcopal bishops and British prime minister, William Ewarts Gladstone chiefly concerning church business. Included among the correspondents are William E. Gladstone, John Henry Hobart, A. F. Winningham Ingram, Richard Channing Moore, Charles Manners Sutton, and Archibald Campbell Tait. Also included are etchings of Richard Channing Moore and of Beilby Porteus, Bisho p of London; and the published volume The House of Bishops (The Churchman Company, 1907).
Arrangement
The 33 items are arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
Index Terms
Persons:
Moore, Richard Channing, 1731-1808-- Engravings.; Porteus, Beilby, 1731-1809--Engravings.; Gladstone, W. E. (William Ewart), 1809-1898.; Ingram, A. F. Winningham.; Moore, Richard Channing, 1731-1808.; Tait, Archibald Campbell, 1811-1882.; Canterbury, Charles Manners-Sutton, Viscount, 1780-1845.
Contents List
- Edward White Benson, Archbishop of Canterbury, England, to Major Culitt[?], England, 1 July 1870., 3 pages. (Folder 1)
  Account of the Whitworth Exhibition allowance together with a balance for L17.13 which was owed, both enclosed; reference to someone trying for a scholarship, taking an examination, and trying for admission to Woolwich.
- Thomas John Clagget, Bishop of Maryland the Protestant Episcopal Church of Croom[?], to the Vestry of St. Paul's Parish, Baltimore, 15 September 1809., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Testimony that the Rev. Mr. Frederick Beasley of St. Peter's Church, Albany, N.Y. had delivered "satisfactory testimony that he has not been justly liable to evil reports for error in religion or viciousness of life."
- Frederick Cornwallis, Bishop of Litchfield and Coventry, England, to Edward Stillingfleet, West Bromwich, England, 28 December 1765., 2 pages. (Folder 1)
  Response and opinion regarding christening children on other days when there is public service rather than on Sundays and holidays.
- Randall Davidson, Archbishop of Canterbury, Lambeth Palace,England, 14 January 1905., Signed notecard, 1 page. (Folder 1)
- George Washington Doane, Bishop of New Jersey, RioundeNew Jersey[?] to Samuel H. Huntington Esq., Hartford, Connecticut, 4 June 1845., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Had heard that candidates for assistant bishop would be Dr. Jarvis and Dr. Horatio Potter and words about both.
- William Ewart Gladstone, All Souls College, Oxford, to Rev. Canon Hemsley England, 7 February 1890., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Thank you note for a record.
- Charles Chapman Grafton, bishop of Fond du Lac, to F. Sallrith [?] Perry, 18 June 1900., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Sends a copy of the Cathedral Souvenir, asks, for a subscription for American Churchman.
- Alexander V. Griswold, Bishop of the Eastern Diocese, Bristol, Rhode Island, to Henry Timothy Pitkin Esq., Washington D.C., 11 December 1809., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Interest in buying the Stephan Brook land.
- John Henry Hobort, Bishop of New York, New York, New York, to Bishop Griswold, 31 January 1815., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Mentions signing a letter to Bishop Clagget drawn up by Bishop White and signed by him as well as by Bishop Moore.
- William Lawrence, Bishop of Massachusetts, Boston, Massachusetts, to [?] Howe. 23 March 19--[?]., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Suggests dates of visit and mentions the service.
- William Lawrence, Bishop of Massachusetts, Boston, Massachusetts, to Master Brandford Washburn Jr., Cambridge, Massachusetts. 3 April 1925., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Explains that enclosed autograph of the Archbishop of Canterbury Randall Thomas Davidson sighs "Cantaur" because "that is the old Latin name for Canterbury." TLS 1p. Including autograph of the Archbishop of Canterbury.
- Charles Harford Lloyd, Eton College, Windsor, England to Sir William H. Hadow, England. 12 November 1893., 4 pages. (Folder 1)
  Details of the preparations for a program of Handel's "Water Music."
- Charles Thomas Longley, Archbishop of Canterbury, Lambeth Palace, England, 7 July 1864., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Asks if his presence is important for a meeting on Saturday because he had made arrangements to leave town that day.
- Charles Thomas Longley, Archbishop of Canterbury, Ashford, England. 8 June 1868., 2 pages. (Folder 1)
  Thank you letter for a copy of lectures.
- William Meade, Bishop of Virginia, Millwood, Virginia, to Francis Wharton, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 12 December 1855., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Additions to book in press of clerical descendants of Mr. Page; alterations made in the concluding clause and at the end of the preface.
- Benjamin Moore, Bishop of New York, New York, New York, to Mrs. Prevost [?], Paramus, New York, 10 November 1780., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Money that was left for her by Mr. Clarke sent and reminder that bills need to be negotiated.
- Richard Channing Moore, Bishop of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia, to his son Rev. David Moore, Whitehall, New York. 27 February 1820., 3 pages. (Folder 1)
  Description of unseasonable weather; sentiments about him D.M. and his congregation; words of inspiration.
- Etching of Richard Channing Moore, Bishop of Virginia, from Churchmans Monthly Magazine, n.d., 1 page. (Folder 1)
- Beilby Porteus, Bishop of London, Fulham, England, 12 August 1799., 2 pages. (Folder 1)
  Sends list for distribution; includes instructions for distribution (1page). Includes AN with list of names (1 page).
- Etching of Beilby Porteus, Bishop of London, published by W. Baynes and Son, 1823, 1823., 1 page. (Folder 1)
- Henry Cooman Potter, Bishop of New York, New York, New York to the Bishop of Fonde du Lac, 25 April 1904., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  States he is "quite at liberty at any time to preform any Episcopal Act in this Diocese that you may be asked for.
- Edward Shillingfleet, West Bromwich, England, to Frederick Cornwallis, Bishop of Litchfield and Coventry, England, 23 December 1765., 2 pages. (Folder 1)
  Advice and direction asked regarding the baptism of children on days other than Sundays and holidays.
- John Bird Sumner, Archbishop of Canterbury, Addington, England to I. Winger [?] Read Esq., England. 15 September 18-[?], 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Notice of receiving a parcel that was forwarded.
- Testimony for Bidlake Bray, clerk, signed by A. Rawsow, Thomas John Ileefiry[?], Joseph William Martin, 11 January 1853., 2 pages. (Folder 1)
  Coantains additional notes by Charles L. Loisely [?] and John Biro Sumner, Archbishop of Canterbury, dated 12 January 1853,
- Charles Manners Sutton, Archbishop of Canterbury, Addinton, England. to "Dear Sir," n.p. 8 December 1813., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Regarding the prospectus of the British Critic; "I approve of it and you may depend upon all the assistance I can give it, in the way of circulation."
- Charles Manners Sutton, Archbishop of Canterbury, Lambeth Palace, England, to the Lord Gwydyr, England, 18 July 1821., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Request for admission ticket for the king's coronation for Robert Blackborne Thoroton Sutton Esq, his attendant at the Banquet.
- Archibald Campbell Tait, Archbishop of Canterbury, Rugby, England, to Rev. Dr. Bliss England, 11 October 1842., 3 pages. (Folder 1)
  Intends to take his degree of D.C.L. on Thursday the 20th; asks for a list of fees.
- Archibald Campbell Tait, Archbishop of Canterbury, Addington Park, Croydon, England to the Dean of Windsor, Gerald Wellesley, England, 6 December 1873., 4 pages. (Folder 1)
  Affirmation that he is capable of taking Princess Beatrice's Confirmation at Osborne.
- William Tempee, Archbishop of York, Bishopthorpe, York, England, to Gribbin [?], England, 24 March 1935., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Sends notification that he is unable to give a sermon on October 21 because he is already giving three sermons that day.
- A.F. Winningham Ingram, Bishop of London, Fulham Palace, England, to "Dear Sir," n.p., 15 January 1909., 4 pages. (Folder 1)
  Lends support for the St. John's School at Leatherhead for the children of the clergy; "The clergy in their poverty can stand many things but what cuts them to the heart more than anything is not to be able to give their sons that chance in life, which they in most cases received themselves."
- Ozi W. Whitaker, Missionary Bishop of Nevada, Reno, Nevada, to Rev. A.B. Hunten, n.p., 20 May 1885., 8 pages. (Folder 1)
  Invitation to become the minister of the church in Eureka, Nevada; description and detail about the town and church.
- The House of Bishops. The Churchman Company, New York. 1907., 1 volume. (Folder 1)